Finding Aid for Pattengill Family papers, 1767-1963
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Pattengill Family papers 1767-1963
Pattengill family.
2 linear feet
852141 Aa 2
Lansing and Ann Arbor, Michigan families; correspondence, photographs, clippings, and other family documents.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was deposited by Mr. And Mrs. Theodore G. Foster (donor no. 1676 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions, 1945-1956.
The collection is open to research.
The Foster family members were residents of Ann Arbor and Lansing, Michigan. Theodore R. Foster was the first United States Senator from Vermont. The family later moved to Ann Arbor, then Scio Township in Washtenaw County, Michigan. One of the sons Theodore Foster was editor of an abolition newspaper. In 1856, this Theodore Foster moved to Lansing, Michigan when he was appointed superintendent of the Boys' Vocational School. Two of his sons served in the Civil War, Charles T. Foster who was killed in 1862, and Seymour Foster who served in Company B, Second United States Sharpshooters. After the war, Seymour Foster returned to Lansing, became interested in real estate and Republican Party politics. He was elected city clerk then city treasurer. In 1893, he was elected a member of the legislature. He served as Lansing postmaster from 1889 to 1893 and from 1897 to 1914. His wife was Mary Woodward. Their son was Theodore G. Foster, a Lansing realtor, but who as a hobbyist became interested in local history and the genealogy of his family.
The Foster family line merged with the Pattengill line in 1912 with the marriage of Theodore G. Foster and Margaret Irene Pattengill. Margaret Irene Pattengill was the daughter of Henry R. Pattengill. His wife was Elizabeth Sharpsteen.
Vincent R. Pattengill, son of Henry R. Pattengill, was also a Lansing realtor in partnership with his brother-in-law Theodore G. Foster.
Although titled the Pattengill family papers, this accumulation is also the records of the Foster, Sharpsteen, and Woodward families. The historian of the family was undoubtedly Theodore G. Foster and his wife Margaret Foster (née Pattengill). Through these donors, the library received different family collections that have been separately cataloged, although they obviously contain inter-related materials. These other collections, also housed at the Bentley Historical Library are Theodore Foster papers (1835-1862); Henry R. Pattengill papers (1861-1939); and the Margaret Pattengill Foster papers (1903-1961).
This grouping of family materials is actually more about the Foster line of the family than Pattengill or Sharpsteen. The papers have been arranged by name of family: Foster, Pattengill, and Sharpsteen, with an additional series of various family members and miscellaneous. Within each family, the materials have been maintained as arranged by the donor into separate files for individual family members. Of particular interest are the papers of Seymour Foster who was postmaster of Lansing and active in preserving the memory of his brother Charles T. Foster who was killed during the Civil War. The Grand Army of the Republic named one of its veterans post in Charles T. Foster's name.
The collection is also of value for the genealogical research materials accumulated on the Foster, Pattengill, Springsteen, and Woodward families.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Antislavery movements--United States.; Education--Michigan.; Lansing (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Lansing.
Contributors:
Foster, Margaret Irene Pattengill.; Foster, Seymour, 1845-1935.; Foster, Theodore, 1752-1828.; Foster, Theodore, 1812-1865.; Foster, Theodore George, 1888-1960.; Foster family.; Pattengill, Craig L.; Pattengill, Victor Romaine, 1887-1943.; Sharpsteen family.; Woodward family.
- Foster family
  - Theodore Foster
    - Correspondence 1767-1819, typescript copies transcribed from letter book (Box 1)
      (include photograph)
  - Theodore R. Foster
    - Correspondence 1851-1865 (Box 1)
      (as published in Michigan History Magazine; includes photograph of the home and store in Scio Township which served as a station on the underground railroad)
  - Seymour Foster
    - Correspondence 1923-1931 (Box 1)
      (include some typescript excerpts)
    - Business and political matters 1875-1935 (Box 1)
    - Post office matters 1889-1914 (Box 1)
      (Foster was postmaster of Lansing)
      (include photographs)
    - Early life and activities 1860s-1930s (Box 1)
    - Regarding Charles T. Foster Post of the G.A.R., including some letters of his brother Charles T. Foster, who died in the Civil War 1861-1922 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellanea 1921-1935, undated (Box 1)
      (photographs and obituary)
  - Theodore G. Foster
    - Correspondence.1902-1952 (Box 1)
    - Essays circa 1910 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings 1938-1960 (Box 1)
    - Miscellanea 1903-1945 (Box 1)
      (mementos and photographs)
  - Margaret Foster (Mrs. Theodore G. Foster, née Pattengill)
    - Correspondence 1903-1954 (Box 1)
  - Foster family (various)
    - Correspondence 1932-1951 (Box 1)
    - Daughters of the American Revolution applications photographs, and miscellaneous, 1919-1941 (Box 1)
- Pattengill family
  - Victor R. Pattengill
    - Correspondence 1898-1936 (Box 1)
    - Essays 1939, undated (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings and photographs, 1943-1961 (Box 1)
  - Craig Pattengill
    - Correspondence 1911-1947 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings and photographs, 1908-1952 (Box 1)
  - Pattengill family (various)
    - Correspondence 1860-1944 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings 1891-1963 (Box 1)
    - Photographs 1909, undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and legal papers 1778-1875 (Box 1)
    - Speeches and business papers 1813-1952 (Box 1)
    - Material on vacations of the Pattengill family 1906-1950, undated (Box 1)
      (mainly photographs)
    - Genealogies of the Pattengill and Sharpsteen families 1920, undated (Box 1)
- Sharpsteen family
  - Correspondence,1856-1951 (Box 2)
  - Sharpsteen genealogy papers 1891-1952 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings photographs, and miscellaneous, 1884-1934 (Box 2)
- Mixed materials and other family members
  - Pattengill and Foster families photographs, undated (Box 2)
  - Genealogy photographs, and newspaper clippings of the Woodward family, 1828-1909 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, including photographs of residences (Box 2)
  - "Behind the Name: Note cards with clippings and notes on origin of Michigan place names (Box 2)
  - Mary Pattengill album of sentiments in appreciation of her work as teacher in Bible class 1860 (Box 2)
  - Clarence Bement diary 1890 and grammar exercise book (Box 2)
  - Diary (author unknown) 1907 (Box 2)
  - Miniature Bible 1865 (Box 2)